Guide to the Postcards of German female impersonators, 1900-1925.
Postcards of German female impersonators,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Postcards of German female impersonators, 1900-1925.
7636
62 items.
Postcards, cabinet cards
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Sixty-two late-Wilhelmine male transvestite postcards portraying thirty individuals in their Damen-Imitator personas, including three images of "Gauze, Canadian Indian Soprano." Sixteen are signed or inscribed by the subjects, with references to gay cabarets in Berlin, Cologne, Kiel, and throughout the country. Five are addressed to Paul Shafer and one to Asta, female impersonators of the period, who are also pictured on some of the cards. One postcard depicts Man de Wirth in costume, circa 1920s. This may be Franz Man de Wirth, described on an 1898 German postcard (viewed online) as the best female impersonator of the time.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Sixty-two late-Wilhelmine female impersonator postcards portraying thirty individuals in their Damen-Imitator personas, including three photographs of "Gauze, Canadian Indian Soprano." Sixteen are signed or inscribed by the subjects, with references to gay cabarets in Berlin, Cologne, Kiel, and throughout the country. Five are addressed to Paul Shafer and one to Asta, female impersonators of the period, who are also pictured on some of the cards. One postcard depicts Man de Wirth in costume, circa 1920s. This may be Franz Man de Wirth, described on an 1898 German postcard (viewed online) as the best female impersonator of the time.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Shafer, Paul.; Asta (Female impersonator); Wirth, Franz Man de.
Subjects:
Germany -- Social life and customs.; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.) -- Germany.; Sex in popular culture -- Germany.; Transvestism -- Germany.; Transvestites -- Germany.; Cross-dressers -- Germany.; Female impersonators -- Germany.; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Sex in popular culture.; Cross-dressing.; Cross-dressers.
Places:
Germany
Form and Genre Terms:
Postcards.; Gelatin silver prints.; Collotypes (prints)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Collecting Program: Human Sexuality Collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Female Impersonators, 1900-1925; 61 postcards, 2 cabinet cards (Box 1)
  Female impersonators
  - Charly Letsche (Box 1)
    - Charly Letsche, 1910; 1; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 13.9 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
      Inscribed.
      Letsche, Charly
      Lubeck, Germany
      Gelatin silver prints
    - Charly Letsche, 1910; 22; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
  - Ferry Krieg (Box 1)
    - Ferry Krieg, Damen-Imitator, 1910; 2; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 13.8 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
      Krieg, Ferry
      Collotypes (prints)
    - Ferry Krieg, Damen-Imitator, 1905; 16; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 8.9 x 14.1 cm (Box 1)
    - Ferry Krieg, Damen-Imitator, 1903; 50; Berl. Phototyp. Inst. Reb. Prager; 14.2 x 9.2 cm (Box 1)
      Berlin, Germany
  - Luzernow (Box 1)
    - Gustav Luzernow - in seinen urkomischen Frauentypen, 1905; 5; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 8.8 x 13.8 cm (Box 1)
      Luzernow, Gustav
    - ? Luzernow ?, 1905; 7; John Koefod, Lichtdruckanstalt; 14.1 x 9 cm (Box 1)
      Hamburg, Germany
    - ? Luzernow ?, 1905; 8; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 13.9 x 8.9 cm; Applied color (Box 1)
    - ? Luzernow ?, 1905; 9; Fletscher, W.; 13.6 x 8.5 cm (Box 1)
    - Luzernow - Chansonetten-Darsteller, 1905; 10; Bebr. Ziebner; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
      Dresden, Germany
  - Asta (Box 1)
    - Asta, 1914; 6; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 8.8 x 13.8 cm (Box 1)
      Asta
    - Asta, 1910; 53; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 9.2 x 13.9 cm (Box 1)
  - Paul Schafer (Box 1)
    - Paul Schafer, 1905; 12; 13.9 x 9 cm; Toned (Box 1)
      This postcard features the same image as postcard 44 in this collection.
      Shafer, Paul
    - ? Schafer ?, 1900; 26; 17.5 x 11.4 cm; Cabinet card (Box 1)
      Schafer, Paul
    - Schafer, 1900; 27; Jensen, M.; 16.8 x 10.8 cm; Cabinet card, applied color (Box 1)
      Rendsburg, Germany
    - Paul Schafer, Soubrettendarsteller, 1905; 44; Dr. Trenkler Co.; 14 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
      Leipzig, Germany
    - Paul Schafer, 1908; 45; 14.2 x 9 cm (Box 1)
    - Performer with tambourine, 1905; 56; 13.9 x 9.9 cm (Box 1)
      Possibly Paul Schafer.
    - Performer with parasol, 1900; 63; 14 x 9.1 cm (Box 1)
    - Ferri Verdini
    - Ferri Verdini, 1900; 21; 13.9 x 8.9 cm (Box 1)
      Verdini, Ferri
    - Ferri Verdini, 1910; 38; 14 x 8.6 cm (Box 1)
  - Rudi Rufino (Box 1)
    - Rudi Rufino, Imitateur de la Soubrette?, 1910; 24; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 13.8 x 8.7 cm (Box 1)
      Rufino, Rudi
    - Rufino ? -Imitateur de la Soubrette, 1905; 39; Lubecker Lichtdruck-Anstalt Schmidt and Gebr. Bottger; 13.8 x 8.6 cm (Box 1)
  - Friedel Schwarz (Box 1)
    - ? Friedel Schwarz ?, 1910; 28; Lubecker Lichtdruck-Anstalt Schmidt and Gebr. Bottger; 14 x 8.9 cm (Box 1)
      Schwarz, Friedel
    - ? Friedel Schwarz ?, 1913; 54; Lubecker Lichtdruck-Anstalt Schmidt and Gebr. Bottger; 13.7 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
  - Gauze (Box 1)
    - Gauze, Canadian Indian soprano, 1910; 30; 13.5 x 8.7 cm (Box 1)
      Gauze
    - Gauze, Canadian Indian soprano, 1910; 31; 13.6 x 8.5 cm (Box 1)
    - Gauze, Canadian Indian soprano, 1910; 58; 14.1 x 8.6 cm (Box 1)
  - Zwegaly (Box 1)
    - Zwegaly ?, 1905; 34; Berl. Phototyp. Inst. Rob. Prager; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
      Zwegaly
    - Zwegaly ?, 1905; 60; Lichtdruck von Trau and Schwab; 13.9 x 9.1 cm (Box 1)
  - Hilmar (Box 1)
    - Hilmar, 1905; 51; 13.5 x 8.5 cm (Box 1)
      Hilmar
    - Hilmar, 1905; 57; 13.5 x 8.6 cm (Box 1)
  - Named impersonators (Box 1)
    - Heinr. Wessels, Damen-Imitator, 1905; 3; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
      Wessels, Heinrich
    - Emil Brunelly - Soubretten parodist, rezitator sopran u bariton sanger, 1905; 4; 9.1 x 13.8 cm (Box 1)
      Brunelly, Emil
    - Myllardo - sopransanger, 1905; 11; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
    - Sissi Lafaly, 1910; 14; 13.6 x 8.7 cm (Box 1)
      Lafaly, Sissi
    - Ernst Loretto, 1910; 15; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
      Loretto, Ernst
    - Niels Holmes, Soubrette-Imitator, 1910; 23; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 14 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
      Holmes, Niels
    - H. Vorst - Soubrettendarsteller u. sopransanger, 1910; 25; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
      Vorst, H.
    - Paul Storsberg - Sopransanger, 1900; 33; 14 x 8.9 cm (Box 1)
      Storsberg, Paul
    - Probasta, das psychologische Ratsel, 1900; 35; John Koefod, Lichtdruckanstalt; 13.8 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
    - ? Hardi Simon ?, 1900; 36; Gebr. Siegner, Kotzchenbroda; 9.3 x 13.9 cm (Box 1)
      Simon, Hardi
    - Paul Sander, 1914; 37; Lubecker Lichtdruck-Anstalt Schmidt and Gebr. Bottger; 9.4 x 13.9 cm (Box 1)
      Sander, Paul
    - ? Eishauer (Eshally) ?, 1905; 46; Nordische Kunstanstalt Ernst Schmidt and Co.; 13.8 x 8.7 cm (Box 1)
    - Taulleur, 1915; 47; Lubecker Lichtdruck-Anstalt Schmidt and Gebr. Bottger; 13.9 x 8.9 cm; Applied color (Box 1)
      Taulleur
    - Gomarre - Die fabelhafte indische Tanz-und Fakirschau, 1915; 48; Anstalt, Gebr. Garloff; 14.1 x 9.3 cm (Box 1)
      Gomarre
      Magdeburg, Germany
    - Alraunen duo, 1913; 49; Fotograf Fritz Frank; 13.9 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
      Frankfurt, Germany
    - Mitzi Kaller, 1910; 55; 14 x 9 cm (Box 1)
      Kaller, Mitzi
    - Man de Wirth, 1920; 62; Haas, H.; 13.5 x 8.6 cm (Box 1)
      Man de Wirth
  - Unidentified impersonators
    - Female impersonator as ballerina, 1905; 13; 13.7 x 8.5 cm (Box 1)
      Ballerinas
    - Performer in costume, 1900; 17; 13.8 x 9.1 cm (Box 1)
      Inscription verso translated as: "A sport [game/play] of nature. 1/2 man. 1/2 woman"
    - Female impersonator in costume, 1905; 18; 13.9 x 8.9 cm (Box 1)
    - Female impersonator with headpiece, 1900; 19; 13.6 x 8.6 cm; Applied color (Box 1)
    - Female impersonator with hat, 1900; 20; Photographische Kunstanstalt Gerh. Merlens; 13.3 x 8.3 cm (Box 1)
      Aachen, Germany
    - Female impersonator in dress and heels, 1900; 29; 13.4 x 8.5 cm (Box 1)
    - Female impersonator in sleeveless dress, 1910; 32; Rembrandt; 13.8 x 9 cm (Box 1)
    - Two female impersonators dancing, 1905; 40; Heldberg, F.; Hansa-Atelier; 13.9 x 8.9 cm (Box 1)
    - Two female impersonators dancing, 1905; 41; Heldberg, F.; Hansa-Atelier; 13.9 x 8.9 cm (Box 1)
    - Two female impersonators as dancers, 1905; 42; Atelier Electra G. Reh; 14.1 x 9 cm; Toned (Box 1)
      Stuttgart, Germany
    - Female impersonator doing a split, 1910; 43; Atelier Electra G. Reh; 8.8 x 14 cm (Box 1)
    - Female impersonator in top hat, 1900; 52; 14.1 x 8.8 cm (Box 1)
    - Female impersonator in ballet slippers, 1910; 59; 14.1 x 9.1 cm (Box 1)
    - Female impersonator wearing lace shawl, 1905; 61; 13.7 x 8.9 cm (Box 1)